Instant messaging is now a major part of everyday communication
and voice typing is becoming more and more common
common because it is quick and convenient
But once spoken language is turned into plain text
a lot of emotional information disappears
The words remain
but important cues like tone
pitch
cadence and emotional nuance are filtered out
This motivated us to ask whether voice
typing could be more expressive
Instead of only being accurate
To think about this
we looked at two lines of previous work
On one side
research on voice typing has made speech input efficient
usable and editable
But it usually treats the transcript as plain lexical content
On the other side
research on kinetic typography and
effective captions has shown that
text can visually express tone and emotion
But these systems are often manually authored or
designed for passive viewing scenarios like
storytelling
videos or captioning
rather than for real time instant messaging
That is why we ask the following question
How can we translate vocal emotion into kinetic
typography to enhance expressiveness in instant messaging
without compromising legibility
and which visual strategies work best
To address this
we first conducted a co design study
then derived a design space with three dimensions
geometry
texture and motion
and finally built emotype-zero as a research probe
to explore these ideas in realistic messaging scenarios
Our first step was a co design workshop with nine participants
We recruited long term voice typing users and
asked them to reflect on how emotional speech
could be represented visually in text
Participants reviewed examples
listened to emotionally varied audio clips
and then created their own expressive text
concepts through sketching and discussion
We documented the workshop
collected the design artifacts
and analyzed the recurring relationships
between vocal cues and visual expression
That analysis led directly to our next
contribution a structured design space
for emotional kinetic typography
The first dimension is geometry
which changes the shape of the text
The second is texture
which adds subtle emotional cues
through effects like color and glow
The third is motion
which uses movements such as pulse
jitter and drift to reflect speech emotion
together
they form a design space for expressive but still
Based on this design space
we then developed emotype-zero to
explore how these strategies could be
implemented and evaluated in practice
Emotype transforms spoken input into emotionally
expressive kinetic typography by analyzing speech
emotion and adapting fonts in real time
Technically
it is a web based messaging prototype
the user speaks into the chat interface
the system captures the audio
analyzes the emotion in the speech
and then uses that information to generate
expressive typography in the final text message
From the user's perspective
the interaction is also simple
tap
speak and view the expressive result
Here
we show how emotype-zero works in a
real world messaging scenario
I'm glad to see you again
oh my God
so happy
Building on the previous example
emotype-zero can distinguish both the type
and the intensity of speech emotion
and reflect these differences through
adaptive typography in everyday communication
With this prototype in place
we then moved on to evaluate how users responded to
these different expressive rendering strategies
so
we conducted a user study with 25 participants
they first completed scripted tasks
where they spoke prepared lines
with different emotions
and then a freestyle task
where they created more natural messages of their own
After that
they ranked the six modes
and participated in an interview
The result showed a clear tradeoff
Geometry emerged as the most preferred overall
because it balanced emotional
clarity with reading stability
In contrast
motion and combo were often seen as more expressive
but also harder to read when the
effects became too strong
Participants also reported that expressive
typography helped them better understand tone
and many said they would be willing to use
this kind of system in daily messaging
From this
we identified three main findings
First
motion is especially effective for
expressing emotional arousal
but too much movement can hurt readability
Second
users prefer geometry as a
practical default for everyday use
while stronger dynamic effects are better
reserved for high arousal messages
Third
kinetic typography plays an important role in
restoring emotion in speech to text communication
helping plain transcription become a richer
and more socially meaningful experience
In conclusion
emotype-zero shows that speech emotion can be
meaningfully restored in text through adaptive typography
rather than treating speech to text
as plain transcription only
Our work suggests that voice typed
messages can also preserve emotional intent
This has important implications for making
voice to text messaging more expressive
reducing emotional ambiguity
and inspiring new effective and accessible interfaces
In future work
we plan to explore lower latency on device models
more personalized control of visual intensity
and accessibility support for DHH users
we hope this work contributes to more
expressive human centered text communication
Thank you very much for watching
readable typography in everyday messaging